All right. Well, we are getting back into our series on the book of Psalms. How many of you guys are excited about that? Thank you, thank you. I have to confess, I'm less excited than you. The Psalms are just, they're hard to preach. They are poetic,
lyrics of artistic brilliance, and I am a simple mind, you know? I like pop country, so I like my music to not make me think too much about the realities of life, and yet here I am wrestling with these ancient texts that are caused to make us think about the deepest questions of life. We said at the beginning of this series, the book of Psalms is the prayer book for God's people.
It is the book of Scripture that doesn't necessarily speak to us, but it speaks for us. It gives us words that those who have found comfort in the shelter of God have been praying to God in the midst of their difficulties, in the midst of their celebrations for thousands of years. It's full of laments, confessions, liturgy, hymns of praise that have been repeated by God's people for thousands of years, and I like that it covers all of the emotions of humanity.
Because within this room this morning, I realized that there are all the emotions of humanity, that there are some of us who are rejoicing, and some of us who are weeping, and some of us who are celebrating victory that we have come through addiction and sin, and we are moving towards repentance and obedience, and some of us are still stuck in the midst of the sin that so easily entangles us, and the book of Psalms is a book that gives us space for all of those emotions and
experiences to happen at once. And there's some stuff in there that's hard, that's difficult, and yet because I find Jesus so beautiful, I remind myself that even the difficult passages, that this book was the hymn book, it was the prayer book for Jesus and our New Testament authors, and they regularly reference it in their lives and teaching. Now, not all of the culture and language translates, and there's a lot of work that we could do in the
Hebrew, but the general human emotions and longings, I think, come through loud and clear. For the rest of the summer, we're going to take one psalm a week, and the speaker is going to discuss how it has helped us pray and relate to God in the past or in the present and how we can, we believe it can help you interact with God in your present moment. That's our continued plan for the summer. I'm going to pray and then we'll get into our specific psalm for this
morning. Holy Spirit, I thank you for the words of the psalms. I thank you for the comfort, the challenge, the conviction, the encouragement, the language they give us as we wrestle through the difficult existence of being humans in a
broken world, and yet humans in a broken world who see you moving towards us in restoration and reconciliation. And God, as we see you moving towards us, we long for ultimate restoration and reconciliation, and sometimes our hearts cry out, "Why is it taking so long?" And you give us language to wrestle with what seems slow reality of your restoration and reconciliation. And yet you answer that question for us in other pages of Scripture,
that you are patient with us, not wanting anyone to be away from you, but you're being slow and patient because you want all people to come to the knowledge of your reconciliation and restoration. So God, as we hop into one of these psalms this morning, I pray you would be present, and you would do what you want to do through this time, that you would speak what you want to speak, that we would hear not from me,
a broken vessel, but we would hear from you, and that anything I say that is not of you would be ignored and forgotten forever, and anything that I say that is from you, God, would speak to us in ways that don't just encourage us for a day or a moment, but rethink the way that we go about living, for your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbor. In Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
We're going to be in Psalm 84, if you have your Bibles and you want to follow along. It is the psalm that Donovan read this morning, the psalm that the song we sung was based on, and I first encountered this psalm through that throwback song that we sung this morning at church camp as a middle schooler, and yes, it is sad for me to admit that it is a throwback song, that my middle school songs are throwback songs.
I'm getting older, and so that is sad for me to admit, but I encountered this psalm particularly in the words of that song at church camp, and like I said at my prayer, church camp was an extremely special place for me. We went to the same place every single year, and I will admit that at the beginning, when I was younger, it really was just an excellent fishing pond for me to go to one week out of the year. I would regularly skip out of chapel sessions
to catch the biggest bath of any camper on site, so I'm very proud of that. I would judge the goobers who were using Cheez Whiz while I had my full box of bath lures. It was just, you know, it was something that I looked forward to, and yet it quickly moved from just a fun week of doing my favorite hobby to the place that I was able to encounter God in really special ways. The Holy Spirit got a hold of me,
convicted me of my sin, and really transformed me from the inside out. And I distinctly remember my relationship with the lyrics of this psalm at camp versus in real life. And I don't know if any of you have experiences like this with lyrics or prayers, but sometimes there are lyrics of songs, worship songs, prayers from the Scriptures. There are these things that are so easy for me to pray with bold confidence.
Specifically for me, this song was so easy for me to sing. Better is one day in your courts than thousands elsewhere. It was easy for me to sing at camp. And then I would come home from camp, and I would be reintroduced to the difficulties of life as a teenager. And we make jokes about that, but I truly acknowledge that teenagers are dealing with tremendous stress and difficulties in life. And I would come home, and we would sing the same song at youth group
as we would sing at church camp, and it quickly seemed way harder for me to sing and believe in me. I would find myself singing the same line with a much different attitude. I wanted to believe it. I wanted it to be true. But it felt far more like an aspirational statement than a reality. And again, I'm sure I'm not the only person in the room who has experienced this with worship songs and prayers from Scriptures. There are lines that sometimes seem so easy
to sing and pray and believe, and other times, the same lyric, the same line, the same prayer from Scripture seems aspirational at best and hypocritical at worst. And if that concept resonates with you at all, I think I have some good news this morning. Because as I reengaged with this song, as I began to study it on a deeper level this week, I was encouraged
to realize that I think this line, this better is one day in your courts than thousands elsewhere. I would rather be a doorkeeper in the house of God than dwell in the tents of the wicked. I believe that this line was somewhat of an aspirational line for the writers of the psalm as well.
See that line, it's the crescendo at the end of a three movement journey in this psalm. It's almost like the psalmist needed to prepare their heart to be able to proclaim that with any
level of truth. It's almost like they needed to remind themselves of what they know to be true about God and themselves before they could get to a place where they could boldly proclaim that. And this is how many of our modern worship songs work as well. The verses, they have the central theme and they're building towards this crescendo, towards this powerful declaration of praise and a chorus or a bridge. It's almost like we need time to remind
ourselves of what is true. In the midst of our failures, our doubts, our grief, before we can honestly and boldly praise God in his presence, we have to remind ourselves of truth. And this is how I read our psalm this morning in three movements. And I believe the psalmists are moving towards this declaration of praise at the end, but they need to remind themselves of some truth along the way.
The psalm, the first movement, starts with this longing for God's presence. It's the psalmist reminding themselves of how good God's presence is, even when they find themselves far away from it. There's this longing, this desire for God's presence.
But that longing doesn't just stay this intellectual, like, happy thought about what it would be like to be in God's presence. This longing moves towards a journey towards God's presence. It starts with a longing for God's presence. It moves
towards a journey towards God's presence, and it's along the journey, as they're moving from a longing for God's presence towards God's presence, as they're actively moving in the direction of God. It's when they get to God's presence that they can offer this genuine praise for God in His presence. And that's the way that I break this psalm down. That's the way I see it happening in the text. So we're going to break it down in those three movements.
This longing for God's presence, this journey towards God's presence, and ultimately this proclamation of praise in God's presence. And that is a really good outline that you guys don't seem very excited about hearing this morning.
Whoo! Thank you. Okay, all right. I'm the only one that's pumped about this. Let's go. First, a longing for God's presence is found in verses one through four. And as we hop into the text, I want to remind us
that even though it looks like the heading at the top of the psalm, it looks like it might not be regularly included in the Scripture. Maybe the translators added it. That is not true. This is in the text. And it says, "For the director of music, according to the gitteth," which is probably an instrument that we don't know what it looks like or what it sounds like, this song is written by the sons of Korah. And I think it's helpful for us to know who
the sons of Korah are as we read through this psalm. They are credited with 11 psalms. They were set apart as the worship leaders and gatekeepers of the tabernacle and the temple. And they have a really unique heritage that I think intensifies the meaning of the psalms that they wrote. Their ancestor Korah was responsible for leading rebellion against Moses and ultimately against God during the desert wandering. If you want to read that story and be depressed,
it's in number 16. That's for you on your own time. But Korah and his family, they were tasked with this tremendous responsibility of taking care of the Ark of the Covenant, the place in which God's presence would dwell. They were responsible for these very important elements of the tabernacle inside the tabernacle. But instead of seeing this gift that God gave them, this responsibility that he invited them to participate in
with him, in relationship with him, instead of seeing this as a gift from the Lord, they looked at Moses and Aaron with jealousy and pride. They weren't content with the role that God had invited them to play, and they rebelled, and ultimately they died as a result of their rebellion. I told you it was depressing. Number 16, write it down if you want to follow up. But in classic God fashion,
he enacts redemption for the descendants of Korah. The children of a leader of a horrible rebellion against God and his dwelling place are now appointed as the official worship team for the dwelling place of God. Is that not like God? To redeem people's stories, like Kent talked about last week, we don't have to let our past define our future. That in God there is forgiveness, that in God there is redemption, that we do not have to be defined by what has happened to us in the past,
or by what we have been handed down by the generations before us, but we have an opportunity to interact with God for ourselves, to receive redemption and forgiveness. God is in the business of redeeming and reconciling. So these are the writers of the psalm, the sons of Korah, worship leaders in the tabernacle and the temple, and they wrote this psalm for a particular purpose. So just like we have hymns and
liturgies in our, we're very low church, so we don't necessarily have liturgies for specific times of the year, but just like our hymn books have hymns specific for different times and different places, I think about Oh Little Town of Bethlehem. Would you guys be super stoked if we sang that on Easter Sunday? Probably not, right? Like we have, we have certain songs for certain times to prepare our
hearts for certain celebrations and reflections. And so just like that, the psalms, different psalms are meant for different purposes, and most scholars believe that this psalm is a pilgrimage psalm, that it is a song that the people of Israel would sing as they were making pilgrimage to Jerusalem, to the tabernacle or to the temple. It was a song that would prepare their hearts to go up to the dwelling place of God.
Three times a year, the people of God would all gather together in Jerusalem for three different festivals, aimed at reminding them where they came from, who they are, and where they are headed.
It's a reminder that we are a called out people of God, that He has brought out of slavery in Egypt, that He has established a covenant with, and that He is in the business of redeeming and restoring and renewing. We are going to a place where God is meeting with
us, and this place is a placeholder because ultimately God's redemption, God's reconciliation, it will not be contained in one specific geographic location to one specific group of people, but God's redemption will come for all people and for all of the earth. It is a reminder of where they came from, who they are, and where they are headed.
And so this pilgrimage psalm, as they're getting ready to head towards God's dwelling place that is for now contained in a specific geographic location, it starts with this longing, this reminding themselves of how lovely is God's dwelling place. Verse one, "How lovely is your dwelling place, Lord Almighty.
My soul yearns and even faints for the courts of the Lord. My heart and my flesh cry out for the living God." The psalmists start by meditating on a longing to be where God is. As they're about to set out on a long and difficult journey towards that place, they're reminding themselves of why the journey is so important.
See, we as a people, as a created people, we were made for communion with our Creator. The first two chapters of the Bible are God's ideal for His relationship with humanity. The whole point of God creating was so that He could dwell with us and so that we could dwell with Him. We were made to dwell in the presence of God.
He dwells with us, and we dwell with Him in submission, worship, and partnership, and yet we all know that the goodness of that story does not last very long. We rebel. We're ripped out of the glorious design because of our sin.
However, from the moment of our rebellion, God begins to move back towards us in fellowship.
This is the narrative arc of Scripture, that we were created to dwell with God in His presence, that we rebelled, that we chose, that's not what we wanted, and that in the midst of our rebellion, God lovingly moves towards us.
In the tabernacle, the temple that the psalmists are talking about, the dwelling place of God, is this moving towards God's redemption story in history. Many scholars talk about how the tabernacle was intended to bring about imagery of the Garden of Eden.
That this dwelling place of God set up in a specific geographic location for a specific group of people, it was to remind all people of where God intended for us to be,
and where God ultimately will get us through His redemption and reconciliation.
The temple is the primary place where God's presence dwelt in the Old Covenant. It is His visible reminder of our past, our present, and our future.
We were made for eternal fellowship with God, but we have rebelled against that plan. God is moving towards us in reconciliation. He is making His presence available to all who seek Him,
but ultimate restoration is coming. God's presence will not be limited to one city or one people group,
but all of creation will experience a restoration and fellowship with His creation. Thank you.
The psalm begins with a longing, a reminding of ourselves that we were created to dwell in communion with God,
and we've been ripped from that place, and yet we know, somewhere deep down inside, we know that we were created for far more than what we were experiencing.
A deep desire was placed inside of us to be with the one we were created for.
And I don't know about you. Sounds like it's just me this morning. Sounds like it's just me and Rachel this morning.
But reminding myself of what I was created for and prayerfully longing for it gets me out of my chair.
It helps me begin to wrestle with my complacency, my temptations, my doubts, and my fears.
And although our journey into God's presence does not require for us,
and this new covenant doesn't require a pilgrimage to another faraway city,
it does have to begin with an understanding of what we were created for and a longing to get back there.
We don't have to go to a faraway city, but we do have to acknowledge that we have been,
we have broken our fellowship with the Creator.
And that He has made a way for us to come back to Him.
We have to, it starts with us longing for that redemption, that fellowship with God again.
They go on in verse three and four, it says,
"Even the sparrow has found a home and the swallow a nest for herself,
where she may have her young a place near your altar, Lord Almighty, my King and my God,
blessed are those..." Sorry. My Christianese kicked in there. It's blessed.
Why do we say blessed when it's Scripture and blessed every other time? Sorry.
All right. "Blessed are those who dwell in your house. They are ever praising you."
There we go. I got it. We made it. These verses, they add some depth and beauty to God's presence.
They zoom away out of the big picture and onto some very specific images at the temple, at the tabernacle of God.
They zoom in to two small birds finding nests in the presence of God's temple.
The thing I love about the names of these two birds in Hebrew is the first one, the NIV translates it.
Where's it at? The sparrow. You know what the Hebrew word for that is? I don't think. That's okay.
I didn't think you would. I don't have the Hebrew off the top of my head, but the Hebrew word for this is literally bird.
It's a nameless bird. It's such an insignificant bird. It's just bird. A bird finds this dwelling place in God's house.
And the second, I got to find it again, the swallow, it emphasizes the most frantic, the most anxious bird of all time. Always worried about something going on.
And I think what the author has in mind here is this reminder that all of creation is welcome in God's presence.
That God's creation is good from the smallest, most insignificant thing to the most important thing by our standards, that God is inviting all of creation to worship him.
The most insignificant, the most anxious, the most worried, the most concerned, they're all invited to dwell in God's presence.
And so if you're here and you think you're insignificant, or you're overcome with the anxieties of this world,
the psalm reminds you that there is shelter and blessing for those who seek it in the presence of God, our Creator.
This leads us out of the movement of longing and into the movement of journey towards God's presence,
because it is one thing to long for God's presence.
It's one thing to sit with a nice cup of coffee on our couch and think about how great it would be to submit and surrender our lives to Jesus.
How many of us stop there? How many of us? Just, we think about, we long for, we love the idea of being in the presence of God, and then our day starts.
The anxieties of life, the temptations of this world, they all creep in, and we actually don't make any movement towards God at all
until we wake up the next morning and get our nice cup of coffee and think about how wonderful it would be to be in the presence of God,
and then do nothing about it. The psalmist is saying that a longing with God has to move us in towards a journey towards God.
All right, verse five. "Blessed are those whose strength is in you, whose heart are set on a pilgrimage,
on a journey towards the living God. As they pass through the valley of Baca, they make it a place of springs.
The autumn rain also covers it with pools. They go from strength to strength, till each appears before God in Zion."
It's this movement from a longing for God's presence to a journey towards God's presence.
The psalmist continues by saying, "Blessed is the one who begins to move towards God's presence,
not just sits on our chair and thinks about how great it would be, but moves towards God's presence."
And the thing I love about the psalms, I said I wasn't super excited about the psalms.
That's true. I'm being real people, real lives here.
But the thing I love about the psalms is like any good poet or songwriter,
notice how I said any good poet or songwriter, acknowledging that the writers of my pop country
aren't really that great or creative. I like it. I listen to it. It's fun.
But like any good poet or songwriter does, they don't oversimplify it. They don't make it cliche.
Rather, they acknowledge the difficult realities of turning a longing into an action.
Because when we live in a broken world, the moment we get up out of our chairs to move towards God,
we will be confronted with the brokenness of this world.
Baca, the Valley of Baca, it literally means weeping.
The poet here, the authors of this psalm are saying, "When you take your longing for God,
"and you stand up and you move towards God,
"you will be faced with difficulty.
"You will be faced with suffering.
"You will be faced with the realities of this broken world."
All of us who decide to turn our longing for God's presence
into an actual pursuit of God's presence
will wrestle with the brokenness of this world.
And I know this from personal experience.
But I know it even more from conversations with many of you.
As a pastor, I get the opportunity to interact with people who are in the deepest wrestling with God
that they could ever imagine.
They have this longing for God's presence.
They're moving towards God's presence.
And yet in the midst of them moving towards God's presence,
all they face is obstacle, difficulty, suffering, pain, temptation, challenge.
It's all attack and it's hard.
And it's like the Valley of Baca, the Valley of weeping.
Scholars have been trying to find where this place actually is.
They can't figure it out.
And I think the reality is, I don't think the psalmist are talking about a real place.
I think they're talking about a metaphorical place that as we journey towards God, we will face suffering.
We will face difficulty.
And what is a person pursuing a genuine relationship with the creator of the universe to do when faced with
infertility, with betrayal, with unemployment, with wayward children, with cancer, with overwhelming addiction, and on and on I could go.
What are we to do when we have a longing for God's presence and we're doing the thing?
We're getting up out of our seat and we're moving towards God's presence, and all we experience is pain and suffering.
What is someone to do? And I love that the psalmists are not trying to disguise that.
They're not trying to hide it. They're not trying to make it cliche or sound like, "Man, if you would just get up out of your chair
and move towards God, everything would be great." You guys heard those sermons? Turn them off.
Moving towards God's presence in the midst of a broken world, you will face the valley of Baca.
You're gonna have to go through it. You're gonna have to suffer. You're gonna doubt.
But you have to keep moving towards Him. Because eventually, your weeping will turn to rejoicing.
And eventually, you will begin to see that the storms in your life will actually produce a harvest of God's goodness if you will allow it.
And this is why it's so important that we do this thing together in community.
Because not all of us are in the same place at the same time, and those of us who are in the midst of the valley of Baca
and need those of us who have come through the valley of Baca and on the other side so that we can cheer to you.
Keep going. Keep your head up. Keep moving forward. Keep setting your eyes on God's presence, on His dwelling place.
Because I know it's hard. I know it doesn't make sense. I know none of it. None of it seems to be working out.
And yet better is one day in the courts of the Lord than thousands else.
As they pass through the valley of Baca, they make it the place of springs. The autumn rain covers it with pools.
They go from strength to strength till each appears before God in Zion.
I don't know about you, but when is the last time you took a long, difficult journey where you went from strength to strength?
Is that the natural way that we go on long, difficult journeys?
I just played nine holes at Rock Harbor a couple weeks ago. It was right before a storm.
I walked nine, which, you know, that's a sacrifice. This course has like 600 feet of elevation change.
I was trying to beat the storm, so the first hole, I sprinted from my shot to my shot to my shot.
The second hole, I kind of sprinted from my shot to my shot to my shot. The third hole, it turned into a jog.
The fourth hole into a power walk. The fifth hole into a walk, walk.
And nothing about my journey could be defined as moving from strength to strength.
It was all moving from strength to weakness. Till the very end, I was like dragging myself up a hill,
thinking why in the world do people do this for fun? This is not fun. This is why they made carts.
They made carts so that we could ride in them. This is, what are we doing?
Anyway, that was a silly illustration to say that difficult journeys lead us from strength to weakness.
So what is it that the psalmist is saying that when we get up and we start journeying through the valley of suffering,
through the valley of pain, what is it about this journey towards God's presence that leads us from strength to strength?
It doesn't make sense. But the reason that as we journey towards God,
that we gain strength rather than losing strength, is because the end destination becomes clearer to us the closer we get to God's presence.
And the end destination for those who are journeying towards God is new creation, is resurrection.
It's not just redemption in this life, but it's redemption in the life to come.
It's that we realize that our life is but a vapor here on earth, and yet God is worried about eternity.
That God's redemption, that his reconciliation isn't just about healing us here on earth, but it's about restoring all of creation back to himself moving forward.
And that's the picture of the temple, the tabernacle. It was this temporary thing that was to remind them of what was to come,
that ultimately God's presence wouldn't be locked in one geographic location for one specific people,
but that it was gonna blow up and go to all the world, that God would bless all of the world through the people of Israel.
And the reason that we can go from strength to strength as new covenant people, when we're suffering, when we're struggling,
when we're wrestling, is because the closer we get to God, the more that we realize that God is more worried about
ultimate eternal reconciliation and redemption than just this life.
And I know it doesn't always make sense, because this is the life that we experience here and now.
But as the destination of God's redemptive plan comes clear into focus, we begin to move from strength to strength to strength.
And I've got a friend, a close friend who I've had the privilege of walking with in the midst of turmoil and difficulty and struggle.
A friend who has lost unexpectedly. A friend who had every reason to say, "Nah, man. I'm good. I'm good with the God thing."
Like, I've given my life to him. And this is how I get treated. And yet, as I've journeyed with that friend and as they've gotten a more concrete vision for God's eternal redemption, his eternal reconciliation, that his plan is ultimately about resurrection, is about bringing death to life, is about bringing the brokenness of this fallen temporary place to a ultimate conclusion through the resurrection of Jesus.
As they've come into clarity for that, I've seen them move from strength to strength. I've seen, and it's not ignoring the suffering. It's not, oh, I'm blessed and highly favored. It's this is hard, but God is good. This is death, but God is life.
This is lost, but God is, He is resurrecting. He is restoring. He is redeeming. And that is how we can move from strength to strength as we get into picture, a clearer vision of what God is ultimately doing in our lives. And it's far less about the 50, 60, 70 years that we have here on earth, and it's far more about the eternal weight of His glory.
Okay. Verses eight and nine, the weird interlude. It's a petition. It's a prayer that doesn't make sense to new covenant people, so I'm not going to spend a whole lot of time on it, but I do want to make it make sense.
It's the only time the psalmist pray for anything specifically. And that, I want to, when we talk about prayer as Christians, 90% of the things that we mean is us asking God to do something for us and for others.
Read the Psalms. That's not what prayer is completely. God's welcoming our complaints. He's welcoming our wrestling. Prayer is interacting with God.
And so we don't have to come to Him and ask for something all the time. Totally fine. We're invited to do that, but that's not the only thing that is defined as prayer.
But this is the only thing the psalmist asks for. They say, "Hear my prayer, Lord God Almighty. Listen to me, God of Jacob. Look on our shield, O God.
Look with favor on your anointed one." And this is a prayer specifically for the king of Israel.
It's a petition that they are making on behalf of their king because the psalmist knows, because the presence of God is centrally located in one location for one geographic group of people,
the psalmist knows that as goes their king, so goes their physical representation of God's presence on earth.
If Israel is not doing well, then God's presence on earth as it is in heaven is not doing well.
They need their king to be obedient. They need their king to be surrendered to Yahweh, because if their king rebels against Yahweh,
then their access to God's dwelling presence goes away. And this is the horrific story of the nation of Israel,
is that they so rebelled against God that the presence of God leaves the tabernacle of God.
They're praying, "God, protect our king." Because as our king goes, so goes your presence.
And as New Covenant people, I have some encouraging news for you this morning,
that we can be confident if we turn our longing to God into a journey towards God, that God's presence will be found.
Because we have a new king, an eternal king, one that is seated on the throne beside God.
The ultimate anointed one and king has done for us what no earthly anointed king of Israel could ever do.
The visible representation of God's presence is no longer tied to a geographic location,
but it is within us and it is secure because our king has won the victory over the consequences of rebellion.
Which leads us to our aspirational proclamation of praise in God's presence.
Better is one day in your courts than thousands elsewhere.
I'd rather be a doorkeeper in the house of my God than dwell in the tents of the wicked.
For the Lord God is a sun and a shield. The Lord bestows favor and honor.
No good thing does he withhold from those whose walk is blameless.
Lord Almighty blessed is the one who trusts in you.
This proclamation of praise that at times seems aspirational or even hypocritical to proclaim
is only aspirational and hypocritical if we are allowing ourselves to be distanced from the presence of God.
If we're choosing something other than a longing for God that is leading to a journey towards God,
if we are journeying towards something other than God, then yes, it will seem difficult to pray.
It will seem even hypocritical to pray.
But if we are allowing our longing for God to turn into a journey towards God,
then it will be easier and easier to pray this with boldness and confidence.
Because when we long for and journey towards God's presence, He will be found.
And when He is found, this is the only proper and genuine response.
It's genuine, authentic praise. When we finally set aside all of our earthly longings,
and pursuits, and when we long for and pursue a relationship with the one who made us and loved us,
we will be able to declare with confidence that better is one day in your house than thousands of others.
Now, it shouldn't be lost on us that Korah, the descendant of the sons of Korah,
that's not the right verb, but you know what I mean. Let's not get hung up on my bad grammar, okay?
Korah had the unique privilege of serving in the temple, inside the inner courts of the temple.
He had this unique place in close proximity to the presence of God.
And instead of choosing to dwell in God's presence, he chose to dwell in the tents of the wicked.
And now his descendants can declare with confidence that they would rather be a doorkeeper outside the temple gate.
They'd rather just be a servant of the Lord than anywhere else.
Their ancestors chose, "I'd rather have my own name made great.
I'd rather have comfort. I'd rather have power and prestige here on earth in temporary tents
than serve the Lord in his house." And because they based their life on temporary things and rebelled against God,
they were removed from the equation, but God now has redeemed their lineage.
And these descendants can now say, "I'm not concerned with the comfort of this world.
I'm not concerned with the power or the prestige.
I would rather be a doorkeeper in the house of God than dwell in the tents of the wicked."
And it often looks like those who are ignorant towards God are prospering,
while those of us who are seeking him are walking through the Valley of Baca.
But in the end, we keep journeying, we keep setting our eyes on the one who made us,
who loves us, and who is in the business of redeeming us.
Ultimately, abundant life will be found in him. Eternal life will be found in him.
We get tripped up again on this no good thing. Will he withhold from those who walk blameless?
Again, we already traveled through the Valley of Baca, so we're not talking about prosperity here, right?
We're not talking about blessed and highly favored. We're not talking about everything is going to go good.
We're talking about good thing as defined by God, not by us.
This doesn't mean we won't be dealt bad things.
It just means that in the end, God will redeem even our most difficult circumstances for good,
because he works all things together for the good of those who love him and are called according to his purposes.
And a lot of times we get to see that on this side of eternity, but not always.
So as we journey towards God, as we long for God's presence, ultimately the longing that we have is about eternity.
About the new heavens and the new earth. It's about the wedding supper of the lamb.
It's about God wiping away every tear from our eyes. Yes, we will see restoration.
We will see good things on this side of eternity. We will see miracles happen, but not always.
And when we don't, we set our gaze on the future.
When God will wipe away every tear from our eyes. When there will be no mourning.
And no pain. And when that will last for eternity.
This is a psalm of genuine praise.
One that feels aspirational or even hypocritical.
Because genuine praise is the result of being in the presence of God,
which starts with a longing for God and includes a journey towards God.
And many of us can't honestly sing this song because our longings have led us on a journey away from God's presence rather than a journey towards.
As I wrap up this morning, I just want to ask us a couple application questions for you to ponder, for you to consider.
I will not answer them for you.
And I don't expect you to answer them for yourselves in this moment.
Maybe write them down and think about them.
But question number one is when you lay your head down on the pillow.
What is it that you are actually longing for?
What is the thing that you have your deepest desires set on?
Is it success? Is it comfort? Is it romantic relationships? Is it health? Is it provision?
It might not be a bad thing, but is it an ultimate thing?
Because any longing that is less for the presence of God in our lives might provide some temporary pleasure,
but it will not satisfy you or sustain you through the Valley of Baca, which we will all face.
And so if our longing is for something less than the sustaining, life-giving presence of God,
then we will hit the Valley of Baca, and we will fall to our knees because there will be nothing to sustain us.
But if we set our gaze, if we set our longing on the presence of God,
the creator and sustainer of all things, the one who was and is and is to come,
then when we go through the Valley of Baca, it will be extremely difficult, but we will move from strength to strength.
What are you longing for, and what are you journeying towards?
Many of us might say that our longing is for the presence of God,
but if we look at your daily life, your weekly, your monthly rhythms, are you journeying towards that destination?
Are you pursuing God's prayer through prayer and fasting, fellowship and solitude, service,
generosity, worship and Scripture? Are the actions of your life showing that the longing of your heart is the presence of God?
Or are we lying to ourselves when we get up in the morning and make our nice cup of coffee and long for God's presence?
Because we can say whatever we want about what our longing is, but what do our actions demonstrate our longing actually is?
Whew, is right, and I'm preaching to myself.
Whenever it gets really heavy in here, just know that I'm talking to me.
And if you get anything from it, then that is God's grace.
But I am preaching to myself.
What is the object of your worship?
If you struggle to genuinely sing praises like, "Better is one day in your courts than thousands elsewhere,"
it's likely because deep down you know that you are worshiping something other than God.
And that is not meant to be condemnation, but conviction and an invitation to repent and move back towards God's presence,
for you will be fully accepted and fully embraced.
Finally, how might this psalm help reorient us towards the most valuable pursuit?
What would it look like for us to pray through this psalm every day this week,
reminding ourselves that any longing other than the longing for God's presence will leave us wanting,
and that the journey towards God will be difficult, but it will be worth it.
My ultimate prayer for us this morning is that we would be a people who long for the presence of God,
who faithfully journey towards the presence of God, even through the valley of tears,
and who, in the midst of the valley of tears, go from strength to strength
and get to a place where we can proclaim with genuine praise
that better is one day in your court,
that I'd rather be a doorkeeper in your house
than have success and prosperity anywhere apart from you,
because I was made to be in your presence,
and anything less than that is cheating myself and cheating those around me.
Church, may we be a people who turn our longing for the presence of God
into a journey towards God's presence.
And may that ultimately lead to the proclamation of praise in His presence,
genuine, authentic, not without questions or doubts or fears or insecurities,
but with faith, believing that you are who you say you are,
that you'll do what you say you do. Let's pray. Father in heaven,
thank you for the Psalms that I didn't think I was very excited about preaching.
And yet again, you remind me that you have the words of eternal life.
Whether it's my favorite genre or not, God, your spirit speaks clearly,
powerfully, boldly to those who have eyes to see and ears to hear.
I pray for each one of us in this room, God, that we would have eyes to see and ears to hear what you want to say to us this morning,
that you wrestle with the beautiful poetic language of the Psalms,
that we would, God, turn them back to you,
that we would use this language we've been gifted from the forefathers and mothers of our faith,
that we would use their language when we don't have words for ourselves.
And God, may this local church be full of people who can honestly
proclaim through tears, struggles, and through pain
that better is one day in your courts than a thousand.
For your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbor.
In Jesus' name I pray. Amen.